Guide to the Mary Beard papers, 1926-1948.
Beard, Mary papers, 1926-1948.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mary Beard papers, 1926-1948.
2641
Mary Beard, 1876-1946.
1 cubic ft.
Correspondence, diary, clippings, addresses, speeches, journals, pamphlets, and notes.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of Mary Beard, a nurse and writer. Collection consists primarily of diary entries recording job related activities; speeches concern public health and nursing issues.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Mary Beard was a nurse and author. She served as Associate Director of the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation, 1924-1938, and was Director of Nursing Services of the American National Red Cross. She also served on the Advisory Committee on Nursing of the New York City Department of Health, 1936-1937.
She graduated from the Cornell University School of Nursing in 1903.
CHRONOLOGY
1876 November 14, born in Dover, New Hampshire to Ithamar Warren and Mary Foster Beard.
1903 Graduated from New York Hospital School of Nursing (later became Cornell University New York Hospital School of Nursing in 1942).
1904 Visiting nurse in Waterbury, Connecticut.
1912-1922 Director of Instructive District Nursing Association in Boston.
1922-1924 Director of the Community Health Association in Boston.
1924-1938 Associate Director of the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation of New York City.
1929 Author of The Nurse in Public Health.
1934 Conferred with honorary degree of Doctor of Humanities.
1938-1944 Director of Nursing Services for the American National Red Cross.
1944 Retired.
1946 Died December 4.
Member of:
National Organization for Public Health Nursing
National League of Nursing Education
American Nurses Association
Episcopalian Club
Honorary member of:
Florence Nightingale International Foundation
Association of Collegiate Schools of Nursing
Honorary degree of Doctorate of Laws, Smith College
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence; diary, 1926-1940; clippings; addresses; speeches; journals; pamphlets; and notes of Mary Beard. Collection consists primarily of diary entries recording job related activities; speeches concern public health and nursing issues.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Beard, Mary, 1876-1946.; Red Cross. United States. American National Red Cross. Nursing Services.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division.
Subjects:
Public health.; Nursing.; Women in medicine.; Women--Diaries.; Nurses.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Journals.; Speeches.; Pamphlets.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Arranged chronologically by record type.
CONTAINER LIST
- Biographical, obituary (The Alumnae News Vol. 21), Spring 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Information regarding Mary Beard papers from Miss Virginia M. Dunbar, Dec. 1944; Apr., May 10, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Mary Beard diary, Dec. 4, 1925, Jan. 4-May 21, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Mary Beard diary, May 28-Dec. 31, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 3-June 29, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Mary Beard diary, July 18-Dec. 30, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 3-May 31, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Mary Beard diary, June 1-Dec. 30, 1928; Jan. 2, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 2-May 29, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Mary Beard diary, June 3-Dec. 31, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 1-June 3, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Mary Beard diary, June 4-Dec. 31, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 1-Dec. 30, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 8-Dec. 30, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 2-Dec. 31, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 2-Dec. 31, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 1-Dec. 31, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 2-May 29, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Mary Beard diary, June 1-Dec. 1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 2-May 31, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Mary Beard diary, June 1-Dec. 31, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Mary Beard diary, Jan. 3-Sept. 30, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Mary Beard diary, Oct. 1-Dec. 29, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Mary Beard diary, Dec. 30, 1938-May 1, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Advisory Committee on Nursing, New York City Department of Health
  - Letters, agendas, reports, May 19, 1937-Sept. 23, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters, agendas, reports, Feb. 25, 1936-Sept. 17, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Printed pamphlets and journals
  - Public Health Nursing (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The American Red Cross Nursing Service, Oct. 1939 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Midwifery in England, Dec. 1926 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - American Journal of Nursing (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The Mobilization of Nursing, Dec. 1941 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The Canadian Nurse, Oct. 1936 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Ohio Nurses Review, July 1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Addresses and speeches, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Addresses and speeches, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Addresses and speeches, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Addresses and speeches, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Addresses and speeches (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
- Miscellaneous material, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Reference journals, 1921, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Reference journals, 1930, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Reference journals, 1935-1937, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Index cards for addresses - seven envelopes of notes (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Index cards for addresses - nine envelopes of notes (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Notes for addresses (Box 1, Folder 40)